<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<LessonContents xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
    <Contents>
        <Content>
            <Key>ChangingStrings</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Learn how to change your strings</p>
                    <p>You must do it</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>FiveBasicChordForms</Key>
            <Text>Some text on changing strings</Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>WelcomeToTheGuitar</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Welcome to the guitar! If you're brand new to the instrument, you should be excited, because you're about to unlock an entire new world of fun, learning, and appreciation. You'll probably make some new friends through it, and you might just one day find yourself with a bit of a gear obsession. Don't worry - it's completely normal.</p>
                    <p>Learning to play the guitar is not easy, so don't be hard on yourself if you struggle. Don't worry about comparing yourself to other players, or try too hard to sound like certain players. Soon you will find your musical influences flowing naturally through your playing. If you love music, then it's already there, you just have to learn how to let it out. As you will hear many times, your tone comes from your hands, which is why a guy like Eddie Van Halen sounds totally recognizable no matter whose guitar or amp he's playing.</p>
                    <p>There's so much stuff to get to (I hope you're excited), but for now let's focus on the absolute basics. The guitar originated as an acoustic instrument in Spain hundreds of years ago. It went through some changes as an acoustic instrument, most notably when steel string acoustics were introduced (which required stronger bracing inside the instrument), but nothing as significant as the introduction of the electric guitar.</p>
                    <p>Early versions of the electric guitar can be traced back to the 1930's, but it didn't really take off until the 50's. By the early 1960's the electric guitar's popularity was massive, and it was in those early years that some of the most iconic electric guitars of all time were built. Even today most of the components on electric guitars are either very similar, or heavily based on the early models from the 50's and 60's.</p>
                    <p>A standard guitar has 6 strings (although these days it's not uncommon to see 7-string, and even 8-string guitars), and is tuned to A 440 concert pitch. The strings are numbered to make them easier to remember. If you're holding a guitar in your lap, the string closest to your feet is the first string. The string closest to your head is the 6th string. You can fill in the blanks for the remainder of the string numbers.</p>
                    <p>Although you may experiment with alternate tunings somewhere down the road, for now let's assume we're in standard tuning. If you were to pluck open strings (meaning you're picking a string without fretting it anywhere on the fretboard), the string with the highest pitch would be the first string, which is an E note. The string with the lowest pitch would be the 6th string, which would also be an E note, just a couple octaves lower. You're going to be dealing with octaves a lot on the guitar so just remember they're the same note being played in different pitches.</p>
                    <p>So the notes for all 6 open strings on the guitar are as follows: 1st string = E, 2nd string = B, 3rd string = G, 4th string = D, 5th string = A, and 6th string = E.</p>
                    <p>In addition to knowing the strings and open notes on the guitar, you should also be familiar with the main parts of a guitar. Since most of these lessons will be written with an electric guitar in mind, let's talk about it's components.</p>
                    <p>Almost all electric guitars have a body made from wood, but the type of wood used can vary depending on where it's made (geographically), and the style of guitar being built. As you can imagine, different woods have different tone characteristics, so if you're making a guitar meant for playing rock or heavy metal, you would want to select a tone wood that suits those musical styles. In this case something like mahogany would be a good choice because of it's darker tone.</p>
                    <p>Attached to the body of the guitar is the neck, which is the part that sticks out from the body. The way the neck connects to the body can vary (some are bolted on, while others are set and glued inside the body), but the purpose is the same - to hold the fretboard. The fretboard is a wooden board that sits on top of the neck, with small metal bars hammered into it, known as frets.</p>
                    <p>Frets are numbered just like strings, and most electric guitars have 21, 22, or 24 frets. Any string can be played on any fret to create a tone, or you can play chords, which are multiple tones being played simultaneously. If you're holding a guitar in your lap, the fret furthest away from your body would be the 1st fret, then you just count up for each fret as you get closer to your body.</p>
                    <p>We're not going to get into music theory in this lesson, so for now all you need to understand is that the notes get higher as you go higher in frets. For example, if you play the first string open (meaning without fretting it), the note is E. Then if you play that same string on the 1st fret, the note is now F, which is one tone higher in pitch than E. If you keep on going up fret by fret, you will eventually reach the 12th fret, which would be the E note again, just an octave higher than where you started. Remember, recognizing octaves on the fretboard is going to be important, but not something you need to worry too much about right now.</p>
                    <p>If you look past all the frets, you'll see a little plastic or bone bar that looks kinda like a fret, and you'll see all the strings are resting on it before connecting into the tuning pegs. This is called the nut. It's important for keeping your guitar in tune. The tuning pegs are little machines that turn side to side. Turning them one way will tighten the string, which raises it's pitch. Turning them the opposite way will loosen the string, which lowers it's pitch.</p>
                    <p>The tuning pegs are attached to the guitar's headstock, which is basically an extension of the neck. This is normally where the guitar's branding is located.</p>
                    <p>Back down on the body of your guitar, if you look directly under the strings, you'll likely see two or three rectangular or rounded bar looking things. These are called pickups and they contain a magnet wound very tightly with wire. Their purpose is to pick up the vibrations from the strings you're playing, and transmit them through the guitar's electronics, through the cable you have plugged into your guitar, and into an amplifier. The location of the pickup makes a big difference on the sound it creates. If you have 3 pickups on your guitar, then chances are you have 3 single coil pickups. The pickup nearest the neck is called the neck pickup, then there is the middle pickup, and finally, the one furthest from the nick is called the bridge pickup, because it sits right next to a piece of hardware called the bridge.</p>
                    <p>There are two main categories of pickups - single coils, and humbuckers. Fender guitars like Stratocasters and Telecasters are most commonly associated with single coil pickups, while Gibson guitars like the Les Paul and ES-335 are most commonly associated with humbucking pickups. Single coil pickups have a bright, open, clean sound, but they also produce a 60 cycle hum, which can be annoying when amplified. Single coil sounds are popular in blues, country, and surf guitar. Humbuckers are pickups wound with two wires, which gives the advantage of removing the hum, but produces a different sound that is lower in frequency and a bit darker, which is more common for jazz, rock and metal playing.</p>
                    <p>There is likely a pickup selector somewhere on the body of your guitar, allowing you to choose which pickup, or combination of pickups, you want to engage. Then you also probably have some knobs to adjust volume and tone.</p>
                    <p>Finally, as briefly mentioned before, you have the bridge, which is what the strings are connected to at that end of the guitar. Some bridges include a whammy bar (also called a tremolo bar or tremolo arm), which is a bar you can use to rock the bridge back and forth with, creating lots of pitch changes as you play. This concept was first introduced with the early Fender Stratocasters of the 1950's.</p>
                    <p>Then there's something called a hard tail bridge, which is a bridge that doesn't move and has no whammy bar. These bridges don't offer all the crazy pitch changes you get from a bar, but they offer better tuning stability, and are commonly associated with guitars like the Fender Telecaster and Gibson Les Paul.</p>
                    <p>There's so much more we could get into, but this is more than enough to get us started. Watch the videos and check out the diagrams below, then when you're feeling comfortable, move onto the next lesson on <a href="/lessons/beginner/changing-strings/">changing guitar strings</a>.</p>
                    <p>Once again, welcome to the guiar. You're going to love it!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
    </Contents>
</LessonContents>