<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<LessonContents xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
    <Contents>
        <Content>
            <Key>ChangingStrings</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Regardless of your experience or skill level, knowing how to change strings on your guitar is a must. The type of guitar you play will determine how the strings are changed, meaning restring an electric guitar is going to be different than restringing a nylon string classical. The following videos and articles will show you everything you need to know.</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>FiveBasicChordForms</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Chords are simply notes from a scale that are being played simultaneously. If you were to play the notes from a chord one at a time, that would be called an arpeggio, which is something we'll get into later on, but for now all you need to know is that a chord is a collection of notes from a scale, being played simultaneously. Although there are many many chords that can be played on the guitar, the good news is that all of them stem from the 5 basic open chord shapes that you're going to learn in this lesson.</p>
                    <p>When you say the chord is being played 'open', it means you're not using your index finger to bar (lay flat across) the remaining notes that your other fingers are playing. Instead, the notes that that you're not fretting with your fingers will ring out in their standard tuning (meaning they're not being fretted). Open chords are normally played on the first few frets of the guitar, but when you get more advanced you'll start finding other places on the neck where a chord can be combined with open strings.</p>
                    <p>So what are the 5 main open guitar chords? Good question! Here they are, and if you ever hear someone referring to 'Cowboy Chords', these are them:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>C major</li>
                        <li>A major</li>
                        <li>G major</li>
                        <li>E major</li>
                        <li>D major</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>If you spell out the notes for those 5 chords, it spells CAGED. Don't worry too much about CAGED for now, but keep it in the back of your mind, because it's an important concept that we're going to come back to regularly. For now, all you need to focus on is being able to play all 5 of those chord shapes without trouble. Be sure to fret the notes of the chord with the tips of your fingers, rather than the pads. The reason you need to fret chords with your finger tips is so you don't accidentally mute other notes. If you're playing an open E chord, for example, you should hear all 6 notes ring out clearly. There should be no buzzing or muting going on. This is going to take practice, so don't get discouraged if they don't sound very good at first. I can promise you that with a little practice, you won't even have to think about playing these chords - your hands will just naturally make those shapes.</p>
                    <p>If you find yourself having trouble playing the chords, you might want to take a look at your wrist position. Instead of having your wrist up at the top of the neck (near the low E string), try repositioning your hand so your wrist is directly under the center of the neck, with your thumb placed directly in the center of the neck. This position shift will make it easier for your fingers to fret each note of the chord using your finger tips, and that's the key to getting your chords to ring out clearly.</p>
                    <p>The following videos and articles do a good job of breaking down these chord shapes and hand positions, so take your time with them. Like all lessons, you shouldn't rush through it just because you're eager to get to the next topic. This concept you're learning is a building block for much more advanced playing. Once you can play all 5 chords clearly, and without much trouble, you'll be ready to move onto the next lesson.</p>
                    <p><strong>Here's a practice tip:</strong> get a metronome and use it whenever you practice. There are free metronome apps for smart phones, there are web-based metronomes that are free, and there are fancy ones you can buy at a music store. It doesn't matter what you get - what matters is that you use it when you practice, as it will help you tremendously with playing in time. In the context of this lesson, you should set your metronome to a slow tempo (~60 beats per minute), and practice strumming chords in time with the metronome. Once you feel comfortable with that, take it a step further by changing chords in time. This will be hard at first, but eventually you'll be able to play the 5 chords (with changes) in perfect time. You know what that's called? It's called playing a song, and you're already on your way!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>HoldingThePick</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Knowing the correct way to hold a guitar pick is an essential skill that beginning players must learn very early on. It's actually a little tricky because there are various different ways to hold a pick, and in my research for creating this lesson, I found plenty of bad examples. Luckily there were also plenty of good examples as well, and they come from some reputable sources. The way this lesson shows you to hold a pick (also known as a plectrum) the same way my teacher taught me many years ago. Since then I've studied with other teachers, and they have all agreed on holding the pick this way.</p>
                    <p>In addition to learning how to hold the pick, the videos and articles in this lesson will help you with selecting a pick. If you don't already know, picks come in various sizes, shapes, and thicknesses. Certain types of picks have become well suited for certain types of guitar playing, so it may take some experimentation with different picks before you find the right one for you. In general, strumming chords is a bit easier with thin picks that have a lot of flex, but those picks are not very well suited to playing solos and scales. So if your goal is to focus on strumming for now, consider a thin pick, but if your goal is to build up speed and have a very articulate pick attack, you're going to need a thicker pick (meaning at least 1mm thick).</p>
                    <p>Based on the type of music I play (rock, metal, blues, fusion), I prefer thicker picks. I have recently fallen in love with a brand from Italy called Esseti Picks - specifically their 'speedy' series. They're nice and thick (at least 2mm), with a carved out dimple for your thumb to fit into. They're hand-made in Italy out of various materials - I have one made of buffalo horn, one made of bubinga wood, and one made out of a synthetic tortoise shell. Each one is outstanding, and everyone I've exposed to them has loved them. They're much more expensive than an average pick (I paid $15 each), but the difference it has made in my playing has been noticable.</p>
                    <p>For now the best advice I can give you is to watch each of these videos and read each of these articles, then go out to your local guitar store and buy a variety of cheap picks (you can get them for less than $1 each). Purchase picks of various sizes, shapes, and thicknesses, then go home and have fun trying each of them out. Over time you will find the style that you enjoy most, but don't feel like you're stuck with this pick for life. That actually happened to me - I played the exact same picks for over 10 years! Eventually I broke away from them and started experimenting with new picks, which is how I came across Esseti picks.<p>
                    <p>Later on we'll get into a variety of more advanced picking and strumming techniques, so it's crucial that you learn the correct way to hold the pick now. Don't rush through this, and be sure to try various picks out. Without realizing it, you're already forming your technique!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>WelcomeToTheGuitar</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Welcome to the guitar! If you're brand new to the instrument, you should be excited, because you're about to unlock an entire new world of fun, learning, and appreciation. You'll probably make some new friends through it, and you might just one day find yourself with a bit of a gear obsession. Don't worry - it's completely normal.</p>
                    <p>Learning to play the guitar is not easy, so don't be hard on yourself if you struggle. Don't worry about comparing yourself to other players, or try too hard to sound like certain players. Soon you will find your musical influences flowing naturally through your playing. If you love music, then it's already there, you just have to learn how to let it out. As you will hear many times, your tone comes from your hands, which is why a guy like Eddie Van Halen sounds totally recognizable no matter whose guitar or amp he's playing.</p>
                    <p>There's so much stuff to get to (I hope you're excited), but for now let's focus on the absolute basics. The guitar originated as an acoustic instrument in Spain hundreds of years ago. It went through some changes as an acoustic instrument, most notably when steel string acoustics were introduced (which required stronger bracing inside the instrument), but nothing as significant as the introduction of the electric guitar.</p>
                    <p>Early versions of the electric guitar can be traced back to the 1930's, but it didn't really take off until the 50's. By the early 1960's the electric guitar's popularity was massive, and it was in those early years that some of the most iconic electric guitars of all time were built. Even today most of the components on electric guitars are either very similar, or heavily based on the early models from the 50's and 60's.</p>
                    <p>A standard guitar has 6 strings (although these days it's not uncommon to see 7-string, and even 8-string guitars), and is tuned to A 440 concert pitch. The strings are numbered to make them easier to remember. If you're holding a guitar in your lap, the string closest to your feet is the first string. The string closest to your head is the 6th string. You can fill in the blanks for the remainder of the string numbers.</p>
                    <p>Although you may experiment with alternate tunings somewhere down the road, for now let's assume we're in standard tuning. If you were to pluck open strings (meaning you're picking a string without fretting it anywhere on the fretboard), the string with the highest pitch would be the first string, which is an E note. The string with the lowest pitch would be the 6th string, which would also be an E note, just a couple octaves lower. You're going to be dealing with octaves a lot on the guitar so just remember they're the same note being played in different pitches.</p>
                    <p>So the notes for all 6 open strings on the guitar are as follows: 1st string = E, 2nd string = B, 3rd string = G, 4th string = D, 5th string = A, and 6th string = E.</p>
                    <p>In addition to knowing the strings and open notes on the guitar, you should also be familiar with the main parts of a guitar. Since most of these lessons will be written with an electric guitar in mind, let's talk about it's components.</p>
                    <p>Almost all electric guitars have a body made from wood, but the type of wood used can vary depending on where it's made (geographically), and the style of guitar being built. As you can imagine, different woods have different tone characteristics, so if you're making a guitar meant for playing rock or heavy metal, you would want to select a tone wood that suits those musical styles. In this case something like mahogany would be a good choice because of it's darker tone.</p>
                    <p>Attached to the body of the guitar is the neck, which is the part that sticks out from the body. The way the neck connects to the body can vary (some are bolted on, while others are set and glued inside the body), but the purpose is the same - to hold the fretboard. The fretboard is a wooden board that sits on top of the neck, with small metal bars hammered into it, known as frets.</p>
                    <p>Frets are numbered just like strings, and most electric guitars have 21, 22, or 24 frets. Any string can be played on any fret to create a tone, or you can play chords, which are multiple tones being played simultaneously. If you're holding a guitar in your lap, the fret furthest away from your body would be the 1st fret, then you just count up for each fret as you get closer to your body.</p>
                    <p>We're not going to get into music theory in this lesson, so for now all you need to understand is that the notes get higher as you go higher in frets. For example, if you play the first string open (meaning without fretting it), the note is E. Then if you play that same string on the 1st fret, the note is now F, which is one tone higher in pitch than E. If you keep on going up fret by fret, you will eventually reach the 12th fret, which would be the E note again, just an octave higher than where you started. Remember, recognizing octaves on the fretboard is going to be important, but not something you need to worry too much about right now.</p>
                    <p>If you look past all the frets, you'll see a little plastic or bone bar that looks kinda like a fret, and you'll see all the strings are resting on it before connecting into the tuning pegs. This is called the nut. It's important for keeping your guitar in tune. The tuning pegs are little machines that turn side to side. Turning them one way will tighten the string, which raises it's pitch. Turning them the opposite way will loosen the string, which lowers it's pitch.</p>
                    <p>The tuning pegs are attached to the guitar's headstock, which is basically an extension of the neck. This is normally where the guitar's branding is located.</p>
                    <p>Back down on the body of your guitar, if you look directly under the strings, you'll likely see two or three rectangular or rounded bar looking things. These are called pickups and they contain a magnet wound very tightly with wire. Their purpose is to pick up the vibrations from the strings you're playing, and transmit them through the guitar's electronics, through the cable you have plugged into your guitar, and into an amplifier. The location of the pickup makes a big difference on the sound it creates. If you have 3 pickups on your guitar, then chances are you have 3 single coil pickups. The pickup nearest the neck is called the neck pickup, then there is the middle pickup, and finally, the one furthest from the nick is called the bridge pickup, because it sits right next to a piece of hardware called the bridge.</p>
                    <p>There are two main categories of pickups - single coils, and humbuckers. Fender guitars like Stratocasters and Telecasters are most commonly associated with single coil pickups, while Gibson guitars like the Les Paul and ES-335 are most commonly associated with humbucking pickups. Single coil pickups have a bright, open, clean sound, but they also produce a 60 cycle hum, which can be annoying when amplified. Single coil sounds are popular in blues, country, and surf guitar. Humbuckers are pickups wound with two wires, which gives the advantage of removing the hum, but produces a different sound that is lower in frequency and a bit darker, which is more common for jazz, rock and metal playing.</p>
                    <p>There is likely a pickup selector somewhere on the body of your guitar, allowing you to choose which pickup, or combination of pickups, you want to engage. Then you also probably have some knobs to adjust volume and tone.</p>
                    <p>Finally, as briefly mentioned before, you have the bridge, which is what the strings are connected to at that end of the guitar. Some bridges include a whammy bar (also called a tremolo bar or tremolo arm), which is a bar you can use to rock the bridge back and forth with, creating lots of pitch changes as you play. This concept was first introduced with the early Fender Stratocasters of the 1950's.</p>
                    <p>Then there's something called a hard tail bridge, which is a bridge that doesn't move and has no whammy bar. These bridges don't offer all the crazy pitch changes you get from a bar, but they offer better tuning stability, and are commonly associated with guitars like the Fender Telecaster and Gibson Les Paul.</p>
                    <p>There's so much more we could get into, but this is more than enough to get us started. Watch the videos and check out the diagrams below, then when you're feeling comfortable, move onto the next lesson on <a href="/lessons/beginner/changing-strings/">changing guitar strings</a>.</p>
                    <p>Once again, welcome to the guiar. You're going to love it!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
    </Contents>
</LessonContents>