<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<LessonContents xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
    <Contents>
        <Content>
            <Key>BasicPickStrumming</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Once you feel comfortable holding a pick and you're able to play at least one chord cleanly, you're reading to begin strumming. As a beginning player, it will be easier to strum with a thin pick (< 1mm), but as you get more experience, strumming with a thicker pick will become much easier. Remember that thin picks are good for strumming, but as not good for scales, solos, and lead guitar playing. On the other hand, a thicker pick (>= 1mm) will be more difficult when strumming, but easier for playing scales and leads. For more help with selecting the right pick, check out <a href="/lessons/beginner/holding-the-pick/">this lesson</a>.</p>
                    <p>The single most important thing to keep in mind in regards to strumming (with or without a pick), is to keep your strumming hand in motion at all times, even when you're not strumming a chord. By keeping your strumming hand/arm in motion at all times, and in time with the beat you're playing to, it will be much easier to strum rhythmically in time with the song. If you were to only move your strumming hand when playing a chord, and keep it still otherwise, you're going to find yourself playing off rhythm. Remember, just because your hand and arm are moving doesn't mean you have to be hitting the strings, so keep those two concepts separate. The strumming hand and arm stay in motion at all times (according to the rhythm of the song), but you only contact the strings when you want to.</p>
                    <p>Other considerations to keep in mind when strumming with a pick include:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>How tight you're gripping the pick</li>
                        <li>The angle with which your pick contacts the strings</li>
                        <li>Strumming with a downstroke versus strumming with an upstroke</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Don't forget - playing guitar rhythmically is hard! It's going to take practice so give it some time. The single best practice tool you can have (besides your guitar), is a metronome. If you don't have one, go on Google and type 'metronome'. The one they give you for free is more than adequate. Otherwise feel free to get a nice stand-alone model.</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>ChangingChordsSmoothly</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>In order to change chords smoothly, you first need to be able to play the chords cleanly. In order to do that, you have to have correct hand and wrist placement for your fretting hand. As a general rule, you want your thumb to be placed in the center of the neck of the guitar, and your wrist should be bent away from the guitar neck. This allows your fingers to arch over the fretboard, which then allows you to fret each note of the chord with your finger tips.</p>
                    <p>Imagine an opposite hand placement for a moment. Your thumb is up near the 6th string, and your wrist is flat up against the neck of the guitar. Your fingers are flatter over the fretboard, which makes it more difficult to fret the strings with your finger tips. Instead, you end up fretting the strings with the pads of your fingers, which causes you to inadverntently mute other strings (and may also cause string buzz). With the exception of chord forms that require fretting notes with your thumb, this type of hand position should be avoided. For all conventional chord types, get that thumb in the middle of the back of the neck, bend the wrist away from the neck, and your fingers will have plenty of clearance to fret each note cleanly.</p>
                    <p>Once you're able to play chords cleanly without any unwanted notes, accidentally muted strings, and no buzzing, you can start working on transitioning between chords. Just like anything else, this mostly comes down to practice and muscle memory. In other words, the more you do it, the easier and better it gets.</p>
                    <p>One simple technique that you can use to help facilitate smooth chord changes is to have an anchor finger. The idea is that you're playing two different chords that have a note in common, so you anchor a finger on that note and keep it there while other fingers move to their new locations, based on the next chord. By keeping even one single finger attached to the fretboard during the change, your hand is much less likely to get out of position. It just gives you a reference point to your hand's placement on the neck. For comparison's sake, try changing chords where you remove ever finger from the fretboard every time you make a change. It's going to be a lot harder to get each finger back in the correct place for the next chord.</p>
                    <p>While anchor fingers are great, unfortunately they're not always going to be possible. There are going to be plenty of times where you're switching chords, and the two chords don't share any notes in common. Here's another idea to facilitate smooth chord changes: always keep your strumming hand in motion. This is actually a staple in rhythm guitar playing, but it's totally applicable here too. You want your strumming hand to stay in motion, and in time with whatever you're playing. Even on the off beats where you're intentionally not hitting any notes, your strumming hand should keep moving in a strumming motion, just without hitting any strings.</p>
                    <p>The way this concept pertains to smooth chord changes is this - if you're playing a song, staying in time is probably the most important thing you can do. Even if you don't play the chord cleanly, by keeping your strumming hand moving in time, you're not not going to get out of sync with the song. It's a fact of life that you're going to blow chords from time to time, but the key is to not let one blown chord cause you to then blow the next chord. Your two hands have to be working independent of each other so that they can always be ready for the next chord. While this isn't a cure all for smooth chord changes, it's an important concept when it comes to staying in time and always being ready for the next chord.</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>ChangingStrings</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Regardless of your experience or skill level, knowing how to change strings on your guitar is a must. The type of guitar you play will determine how the strings are changed, meaning restring an electric guitar is going to be different than restringing a nylon string classical. The following videos and articles will show you everything you need to know.</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>FiveBasicChordForms</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Chords are simply notes from a scale that are being played simultaneously. If you were to play the notes from a chord one at a time, that would be called an arpeggio, which is something we'll get into later on, but for now all you need to know is that a chord is a collection of notes from a scale, being played simultaneously. Although there are many many chords that can be played on the guitar, the good news is that all of them stem from the 5 basic open chord shapes that you're going to learn in this lesson.</p>
                    <p>When you say the chord is being played 'open', it means you're not using your index finger to bar (lay flat across) the remaining notes that your other fingers are playing. Instead, the notes that that you're not fretting with your fingers will ring out in their standard tuning (meaning they're not being fretted). Open chords are normally played on the first few frets of the guitar, but when you get more advanced you'll start finding other places on the neck where a chord can be combined with open strings.</p>
                    <p>So what are the 5 main open guitar chords? Good question! Here they are, and if you ever hear someone referring to 'Cowboy Chords', these are them:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>C major</li>
                        <li>A major</li>
                        <li>G major</li>
                        <li>E major</li>
                        <li>D major</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>If you spell out the notes for those 5 chords, it spells CAGED. Don't worry too much about CAGED for now, but keep it in the back of your mind, because it's an important concept that we're going to come back to regularly. For now, all you need to focus on is being able to play all 5 of those chord shapes without trouble. Be sure to fret the notes of the chord with the tips of your fingers, rather than the pads. The reason you need to fret chords with your finger tips is so you don't accidentally mute other notes. If you're playing an open E chord, for example, you should hear all 6 notes ring out clearly. There should be no buzzing or muting going on. This is going to take practice, so don't get discouraged if they don't sound very good at first. I can promise you that with a little practice, you won't even have to think about playing these chords - your hands will just naturally make those shapes.</p>
                    <p>If you find yourself having trouble playing the chords, you might want to take a look at your wrist position. Instead of having your wrist up at the top of the neck (near the low E string), try repositioning your hand so your wrist is directly under the center of the neck, with your thumb placed directly in the center of the neck. This position shift will make it easier for your fingers to fret each note of the chord using your finger tips, and that's the key to getting your chords to ring out clearly.</p>
                    <p>The following videos and articles do a good job of breaking down these chord shapes and hand positions, so take your time with them. Like all lessons, you shouldn't rush through it just because you're eager to get to the next topic. This concept you're learning is a building block for much more advanced playing. Once you can play all 5 chords clearly, and without much trouble, you'll be ready to move onto the next lesson.</p>
                    <p><strong>Here's a practice tip:</strong> get a metronome and use it whenever you practice. There are free metronome apps for smart phones, there are web-based metronomes that are free, and there are fancy ones you can buy at a music store. It doesn't matter what you get - what matters is that you use it when you practice, as it will help you tremendously with playing in time. In the context of this lesson, you should set your metronome to a slow tempo (~60 beats per minute), and practice strumming chords in time with the metronome. Once you feel comfortable with that, take it a step further by changing chords in time. This will be hard at first, but eventually you'll be able to play the 5 chords (with changes) in perfect time. You know what that's called? It's called playing a song, and you're already on your way!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>HoldingThePick</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Knowing the correct way to hold a guitar pick is an essential skill that beginning players must learn very early on. It's actually a little tricky because there are various different ways to hold a pick, and in my research for creating this lesson, I found plenty of bad examples. Luckily there were also plenty of good examples as well, and they come from some reputable sources. The way this lesson shows you to hold a pick (also known as a plectrum) the same way my teacher taught me many years ago. Since then I've studied with other teachers, and they have all agreed on holding the pick this way.</p>
                    <p>In addition to learning how to hold the pick, the videos and articles in this lesson will help you with selecting a pick. If you don't already know, picks come in various sizes, shapes, and thicknesses. Certain types of picks have become well suited for certain types of guitar playing, so it may take some experimentation with different picks before you find the right one for you. In general, strumming chords is a bit easier with thin picks that have a lot of flex, but those picks are not very well suited to playing solos and scales. So if your goal is to focus on strumming for now, consider a thin pick, but if your goal is to build up speed and have a very articulate pick attack, you're going to need a thicker pick (meaning at least 1mm thick).</p>
                    <p>Based on the type of music I play (rock, metal, blues, fusion), I prefer thicker picks. I have recently fallen in love with a brand from Italy called Esseti Picks - specifically their 'speedy' series. They're nice and thick (at least 2mm), with a carved out dimple for your thumb to fit into. They're hand-made in Italy out of various materials - I have one made of buffalo horn, one made of bubinga wood, and one made out of a synthetic tortoise shell. Each one is outstanding, and everyone I've exposed to them has loved them. They're much more expensive than an average pick (I paid $15 each), but the difference it has made in my playing has been noticable.</p>
                    <p>For now the best advice I can give you is to watch each of these videos and read each of these articles, then go out to your local guitar store and buy a variety of cheap picks (you can get them for less than $1 each). Purchase picks of various sizes, shapes, and thicknesses, then go home and have fun trying each of them out. Over time you will find the style that you enjoy most, but don't feel like you're stuck with this pick for life. That actually happened to me - I played the exact same picks for over 10 years! Eventually I broke away from them and started experimenting with new picks, which is how I came across Esseti picks.<p>
                    <p>Later on we'll get into a variety of more advanced picking and strumming techniques, so it's crucial that you learn the correct way to hold the pick now. Don't rush through this, and be sure to try various picks out. Without realizing it, you're already forming your technique!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>MusicTheoryBasicsPart1</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>It's not uncommon for the eyes of guitar players to begin to gloss over when the topic of music theory comes up. The reason for this is that because the guitar is such a pattern-based instrument, many (maybe even most) of us never learned theory to begin with. We learned the guitar by learning to play our favorite songs, learning basic open chords and bar chords, learning a few solo patterns, and just running with it. While not 'knowing' your instrument was a badge of pride for many punk and grunge bands, even some of the all-time greats like Stevie Ray Vaughan readily admitted that they couldn't read music, and didn't come from a traditional scholastic musical background. They learned to play with feel, and from their heart, and that was enough to take them far.</p>
                    <p>That said, it's well worth the time investment to at least learn the basics of music theory, and what that looks like on the guitar. That way when you read or hear someone say "The blues scale is just the minor pentatonic scale with an added flat 5th" you will understand what they mean. One thing to keep in mind when it comes to learning theory is this - you should study it, learn it, and understand it, then try to forget all of it when playing in a live situation. The reason is simple - when you're thinking too much about what to play, your music starts sounding very mechanical and predictable. What you want is to learn the theory, and put it into practice on the guitar so that it becomes a natural part of your playing, rather than something you have to think about while playing.</p>
                    <p>For this lesson, the only thing we're going to focus on is learning the major scale. By the end of this lesson you will know how to build a major scale in any key because you will know all the notes of the chromatic scale, and you'll know the intervals that make up a major scale. If this sounds intimidating, it's only because of the unfamiliar verbiage, however I promise the concepts being discussed in this lesson are very simple.</p>
                    <p>Okay, so before we even talk about the major scale, let's just talk about notes. There are 12 unique notes in each octave, then you move onto the next octave where the same 12 notes get repeated in a new pitch (higher or lower). On a guitar, you can experience these 11 unique notes by choosing any single string you want, plucking that string open (meaning don't fret it), then pluck it again while fretting it on the first fret, then pluck it again while fretting the second fret, and continuing this all the way up to the 11th fret. By the time you reach that 11th fret, you will have played every note in the musical chromatic scale. Once you reach the 12th fret, you'll be playing the same note you played when you played the string open at the beginning, except now you're playing that note in a higher octave.</p>
                    <p>The chromatic scale doesn't really sound good because you're just playing every note there is, but it can be useful in small quantities for certain types of soloing. Let's take a look at the names of every note in the chromatic scale, starting from A</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>A</li>
                        <li>A#</li>
                        <li>B</li>
                        <li>C</li>
                        <li>C#</li>
                        <li>D</li>
                        <li>D#</li>
                        <li>E</li>
                        <li>F</li>
                        <li>F#</li>
                        <li>G</li>
                        <li>G#</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Notice those # signs? Those are pronouced "sharp", so you've got A sharp, C sharp, D sharp, F sharp, and G sharp. Another important thing to notice is that not every whole note has a sharp associated with it. Notice that there is no B# or E#. The musical reasons for this are beyond the scope of this lesson, so here's what you need to know. Every note in that list is a half-step apart from the next note on the list. "Steps" are music's way of measuring the distance between notes. When you hear anyone referring to steps, you generally only going to hear the terms "step" or "half-step". The distance between C and C# is a half-step. Meanwhile the distance between C and D is a whole step.</p>
                    <p>Going back to our guitar example where we picked an open string, then picked that string on each fret from 1 to 11, lets do that again, but let's specifically do it on the 5th string, which is the A string. Looking at the list above, play the open A string, then play it on the first fret. Now you're playing A#. Now play that string on the second fret and you're playing a B note. Play it on the third fret and you're playing a C note. Continue this all the way up to the 11th fret and you will have played each note in the list above in that exact order. Then play the 5th string on the 12th fret and you're now playing another A note, except this time it's being played one octave higher in pitch than when you played it open.</p>
                    <p>The other important thing to learn here is that a half-step is equal to one fret on the guitar. So if you're playing an A note on the open 5th string, then you play the first fret of the 5th string, you're now playing an A#, which is a half-step above A. This rule applies literally everywhere on the guitar fretboard. No matter which note you're playing, if you were to fret that note one fret higher, you would then being playing a note that is a half-step higher than the original note.</p>
                    <p>So a one fret increment is equal to a half-step increment. What about a whole step increment? Well, whole steps are always two frets on the guitar. Always. So for example, if I'm playing a C note on the 5th string 3rd fret, going a whole step up to D would be to play the same string on the 5th fret.</p>
                    <p>Remember how in that list above several of the notes had a # next to them? Well, that's a totally valid way of writing every note, but it's not the only way. Instead of using sharps, we could also write the notes of the chromatic scale with b (flats), like this:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>A</li>
                        <li>Bb</li>
                        <li>B</li>
                        <li>C</li>
                        <li>Db</li>
                        <li>D</li>
                        <li>Eb</li>
                        <li>E</li>
                        <li>F</li>
                        <li>Gb</li>
                        <li>G</li>
                        <li>Ab</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Those are literally the exact same tones as the ones in the first list, but we're using their flat names instead of their sharp names. What this means is that while A# and Bb are different in name, they are identical in tone, meaning for all intents and purposes they are the same note. From a playing perspective, it's impossible to distinuish an A# from a Bb, and the same thing goes for C# and Db, same for D# and Eb, same for F# and Gb, and same for G# and Ab.</p>
                    <p>Although it's totally valid to call a note Gb, it would be uncommon to hear a guitar player say that because we normally say F#. Similarly, guitar players tend to say Bb rather than A#. Again, neither would be wrong from a musical perspective, it's just more of a convention thing.</p>
                    <p>So before we get to the major scale let's just recap a couple things:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>The chromatic scale consists of 12 unique notes</li>
                        <li>Every one of these notes is a half-step apart from the next or previous note</li>
                        <li>Whole notes are normally a whole step apart (A-B, C-D, D-E, F-G, & G-A) but B-C and E-F are only a half-step apart</li>
                        <li>Half-steps are represented on the guitar by a distance of 1 fret</li>
                        <li>Whole steps are represented on the guitar by a distance of 2 frets</li>
                        <li>The in between notes can be referenced with their corresponding sharp or flat sign</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Okay, with this knowledge in mind, learning the major scale is really easy. The most difficult part of this lesson is now behind us, but before we discuss how to build a major scale, we need to know what a major scale sounds like. If you've ever heard someone singing "Do, Re, Mi, Fa, So, La, Ti, Do", that's the major scale. If you don't know what I'm talking about, don't worry, just have a look at the videos below. I'm sure everyone will instantly recognize the major scale because it is literally the foundation of all western music, which is why we're learning it first.</p>
                    <p>Looking at the Do Re Mi example, we can see that there is a total of 8 notes in the scale, but 2 of them are Do, meaning they are an octave apart. This means that there are 7 distinct notes in the major scale. Just sing "Do, Re, Mi, Fa, So, La, Ti" and you will have sung all 7 notes. The reason we normally finish it with a second "Do" at the end is because it's the root note of the scale, so the music naturally resolves there. This raises an important point - no matter which key you want to play the major scale in, the root note of that key is the first note you play. So for example, if you want to play a C major scale, the first note to play in that scale is C. Same goes for any other key.</p>
                    <p>Ready to learn how to build a major scale in any key? It's actually quite easy, you just have to remember this basic pattern: Whole, Whole, Half, Whole, Whole, Whole, Half. Another way to say it would be: two wholes, half, three wholes, half. As you may have guessed, we're referring to whole steps and half steps. Basically, all you have to do is pick a key, play the root note of that key on your instrument, then count up in the increments I just listed to play the remaining notes of the scale. Let's look at an example.</p>
                    <p>Music teachers always initially teach the major scale in the key of C, because it contains no sharps or flats, so let's start there. I'm going to list all the notes of the chromatic scale, starting at C, and the notes that are in the C major scale will be bolded.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li><strong>C</strong></li>
                        <li><small>C#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>D</strong></li>
                        <li><small>D#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>E</strong></li>
                        <li><strong>F</strong></li>
                        <li><small>F#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>G</strong></li>
                        <li><small>G#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>A</strong></li>
                        <li><small>A#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>B</strong></li>
                        <li><strong>C</strong></li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Looking at this, now recite the pattern from before: Whole step, Whole step, Half step, Whole step, Whole step, Whole step, Half step. From C-D is a whole step, from D-E is a whole step, E-F is a half step, F-G is a whole step, G-A is a whole step, A-B is a whole step, and B-C is a half-step. It's perfect, and as previously mentioned, the C major scale contains no sharps or flats, so it's really easy to memorize.</p>
                    <p>Let's do another example using a different key. Since I was creating the lists above starting with A, let's write out the A chromatic scale (like before) and bold the notes of the A major scale.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li><strong>A</strong></li>
                        <li><small>A#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>B</strong></li>
                        <li><small>C</small></li>
                        <li><strong>C#</strong></li>
                        <li><strong>D</strong></li>
                        <li><small>D#</small></li>
                        <li><strong>E</strong></li>
                        <li><small>F</small></li>
                        <li><strong>F#</strong></li>
                        <li><small>G</small></li>
                        <li><strong>G#</strong></li>
                        <li><strong>A</strong></li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>So the notes of the A major scale are A, B, C#, D, E, F#, & G# (or Ab). This means that the A major scale contains 3 sharps or flats. Using this system, you can easily create the major scale for any of the 12 keys in the chromatic scale.</p>
                    <p>I know this is a lot to digest, so for now we're going to leave it at that. In future lessons we will discuss how the major scale is used as a reference point for other scales and chords. While I hope this explanation was extensive enough to demonstrate the necessary concepts without going too deep into detail, I realize that stuff like this can be explained in many different ways, so I have selected the following videos and articles to give you more perspectives on the same concept. Before moving on, your goal should be to understand the following:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>The chromatic scale represents every tone in western music</li>
                        <li>There are 12 notes in the chromatic scale</li>
                        <li>You can build a major scale from any single note in the chromatic scale</li>
                        <li>The 'distance' (known in music as intervals) between notes is measured in half-steps and whole steps</li>
                        <li>A half-step is represented on the guitar by moving up or down one fret</li>
                        <li>A whole step is represented on the guitar by moving up or down two frets</li>
                        <li>B-C and E-F are the only whole notes in music who are separated by a half-step. The rest of the whole notes have a sharp/flat between them.</li>
                        <li>The pattern for building a major scale is: Whole step, Whole step, Half step, Whole step, Whole step, Whole step, Half step (2 wholes, half, 3 wholes, half)</li>
                        <li>You can build any major scale for any key by starting with the root note of the key, then using that pattern to select the remaining notes.</li>
                    </ul>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
        <Content>
            <Key>WelcomeToTheGuitar</Key>
            <Text>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Welcome to the guitar! If you're brand new to the instrument, you should be excited, because you're about to unlock an entire new world of fun, learning, and appreciation. You'll probably make some new friends through it, and you might just one day find yourself with a bit of a gear obsession. Don't worry - it's completely normal.</p>
                    <p>Learning to play the guitar is not easy, so don't be hard on yourself if you struggle. Don't worry about comparing yourself to other players, or try too hard to sound like certain players. Soon you will find your musical influences flowing naturally through your playing. If you love music, then it's already there, you just have to learn how to let it out. As you will hear many times, your tone comes from your hands, which is why a guy like Eddie Van Halen sounds totally recognizable no matter whose guitar or amp he's playing.</p>
                    <p>There's so much stuff to get to (I hope you're excited), but for now let's focus on the absolute basics. The guitar originated as an acoustic instrument in Spain hundreds of years ago. It went through some changes as an acoustic instrument, most notably when steel string acoustics were introduced (which required stronger bracing inside the instrument), but nothing as significant as the introduction of the electric guitar.</p>
                    <p>Early versions of the electric guitar can be traced back to the 1930's, but it didn't really take off until the 50's. By the early 1960's the electric guitar's popularity was massive, and it was in those early years that some of the most iconic electric guitars of all time were built. Even today most of the components on electric guitars are either very similar, or heavily based on the early models from the 50's and 60's.</p>
                    <p>A standard guitar has 6 strings (although these days it's not uncommon to see 7-string, and even 8-string guitars), and is tuned to A 440 concert pitch. The strings are numbered to make them easier to remember. If you're holding a guitar in your lap, the string closest to your feet is the first string. The string closest to your head is the 6th string. You can fill in the blanks for the remainder of the string numbers.</p>
                    <p>Although you may experiment with alternate tunings somewhere down the road, for now let's assume we're in standard tuning. If you were to pluck open strings (meaning you're picking a string without fretting it anywhere on the fretboard), the string with the highest pitch would be the first string, which is an E note. The string with the lowest pitch would be the 6th string, which would also be an E note, just a couple octaves lower. You're going to be dealing with octaves a lot on the guitar so just remember they're the same note being played in different pitches.</p>
                    <p>So the notes for all 6 open strings on the guitar are as follows: 1st string = E, 2nd string = B, 3rd string = G, 4th string = D, 5th string = A, and 6th string = E.</p>
                    <p>In addition to knowing the strings and open notes on the guitar, you should also be familiar with the main parts of a guitar. Since most of these lessons will be written with an electric guitar in mind, let's talk about it's components.</p>
                    <p>Almost all electric guitars have a body made from wood, but the type of wood used can vary depending on where it's made (geographically), and the style of guitar being built. As you can imagine, different woods have different tone characteristics, so if you're making a guitar meant for playing rock or heavy metal, you would want to select a tone wood that suits those musical styles. In this case something like mahogany would be a good choice because of it's darker tone.</p>
                    <p>Attached to the body of the guitar is the neck, which is the part that sticks out from the body. The way the neck connects to the body can vary (some are bolted on, while others are set and glued inside the body), but the purpose is the same - to hold the fretboard. The fretboard is a wooden board that sits on top of the neck, with small metal bars hammered into it, known as frets.</p>
                    <p>Frets are numbered just like strings, and most electric guitars have 21, 22, or 24 frets. Any string can be played on any fret to create a tone, or you can play chords, which are multiple tones being played simultaneously. If you're holding a guitar in your lap, the fret furthest away from your body would be the 1st fret, then you just count up for each fret as you get closer to your body.</p>
                    <p>We're not going to get into music theory in this lesson, so for now all you need to understand is that the notes get higher as you go higher in frets. For example, if you play the first string open (meaning without fretting it), the note is E. Then if you play that same string on the 1st fret, the note is now F, which is one tone higher in pitch than E. If you keep on going up fret by fret, you will eventually reach the 12th fret, which would be the E note again, just an octave higher than where you started. Remember, recognizing octaves on the fretboard is going to be important, but not something you need to worry too much about right now.</p>
                    <p>If you look past all the frets, you'll see a little plastic or bone bar that looks kinda like a fret, and you'll see all the strings are resting on it before connecting into the tuning pegs. This is called the nut. It's important for keeping your guitar in tune. The tuning pegs are little machines that turn side to side. Turning them one way will tighten the string, which raises it's pitch. Turning them the opposite way will loosen the string, which lowers it's pitch.</p>
                    <p>The tuning pegs are attached to the guitar's headstock, which is basically an extension of the neck. This is normally where the guitar's branding is located.</p>
                    <p>Back down on the body of your guitar, if you look directly under the strings, you'll likely see two or three rectangular or rounded bar looking things. These are called pickups and they contain a magnet wound very tightly with wire. Their purpose is to pick up the vibrations from the strings you're playing, and transmit them through the guitar's electronics, through the cable you have plugged into your guitar, and into an amplifier. The location of the pickup makes a big difference on the sound it creates. If you have 3 pickups on your guitar, then chances are you have 3 single coil pickups. The pickup nearest the neck is called the neck pickup, then there is the middle pickup, and finally, the one furthest from the nick is called the bridge pickup, because it sits right next to a piece of hardware called the bridge.</p>
                    <p>There are two main categories of pickups - single coils, and humbuckers. Fender guitars like Stratocasters and Telecasters are most commonly associated with single coil pickups, while Gibson guitars like the Les Paul and ES-335 are most commonly associated with humbucking pickups. Single coil pickups have a bright, open, clean sound, but they also produce a 60 cycle hum, which can be annoying when amplified. Single coil sounds are popular in blues, country, and surf guitar. Humbuckers are pickups wound with two wires, which gives the advantage of removing the hum, but produces a different sound that is lower in frequency and a bit darker, which is more common for jazz, rock and metal playing.</p>
                    <p>There is likely a pickup selector somewhere on the body of your guitar, allowing you to choose which pickup, or combination of pickups, you want to engage. Then you also probably have some knobs to adjust volume and tone.</p>
                    <p>Finally, as briefly mentioned before, you have the bridge, which is what the strings are connected to at that end of the guitar. Some bridges include a whammy bar (also called a tremolo bar or tremolo arm), which is a bar you can use to rock the bridge back and forth with, creating lots of pitch changes as you play. This concept was first introduced with the early Fender Stratocasters of the 1950's.</p>
                    <p>Then there's something called a hard tail bridge, which is a bridge that doesn't move and has no whammy bar. These bridges don't offer all the crazy pitch changes you get from a bar, but they offer better tuning stability, and are commonly associated with guitars like the Fender Telecaster and Gibson Les Paul.</p>
                    <p>There's so much more we could get into, but this is more than enough to get us started. Watch the videos and check out the diagrams below, then when you're feeling comfortable, move onto the next lesson on <a href="/lessons/beginner/changing-strings/">changing guitar strings</a>.</p>
                    <p>Once again, welcome to the guiar. You're going to love it!</p>
                ]]>
            </Text>
        </Content>
    </Contents>
</LessonContents>